<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>MeshCMS structure</title>

  <subtitle>This article illustrates the various components of MeshCMS and how
  they can be upgraded to a new version. Some advanced users might want to
  customize MeshCMS further, but here we deal with the more usual scenario of
  a normal installation and usage.</subtitle>

  <section>
    <title>/admin</title>

    <para>This directory should be left unmodified by the user, but he can
    choose to move it anywhere, for example if he needs to use the /admin dir
    for other purposes. If we require this dir to stay there, we can simply
    replace it with the new one when upgrading.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/module_templates</title>

    <para>This dir is just a default for custom module templates and can be
    left unmodified. The user can move it.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/themes</title>

    <para>Contains some examples of themes. The user is free to delete them.
    When upgrading, the installation might re-install the themes, but this is
    not required: if the user wants to try the new themes (if any), he better
    installs a test application separately. Further, the user can move this
    dir, so it is better to leave it untouched.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/web.xml</title>

    <para>Hard task here! The new version might require some changes, but
    simply replacing this file might be dangerous, as the user might have
    customized it. Maybe it's better to let the user know that he needs to
    edit something there.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/sitemesh.xml</title>

    <para>Some users might want to customize this file, but in most cases this
    is not needed. Anyway we need to ask permission before replacing
    it.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/decorators.xml</title>

    <para>This file contains the root element only. It is not needed by
    MeshCMS, but SiteMesh requires it to be there. No problem if someone
    customizes it: we don't need to replace it for the moment.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/tlds</title>

    <para>All files contained here belong to their libraries, except
    meshcms-taglib.tld. If the user does not upgrade libraries by himself, we
    can simply replace all four files with the new ones.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/libs</title>

    <para>Again, six JAR files that can be replaced with the new ones, without
    touching other libs added by the user.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/meshcms/filetypes.txt</title>

    <para>A table of extensions. Some users might want to edit it, but
    generally we can replace it with the new one.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>/WEB-INF/classes</title>

    <para>Some users might add some classes, but the subdirectory
    com/cromoteca should be replaced with the new one without any issue.
    org.clapper.util.text.* will not be included in the following
    releases.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Items installed the first time only</title>

    <para>Some elements need to be installed in case of a fresh install, but
    they shouldn't be upgraded:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>/index.html (just an example)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>/WEB-INF/meshcms/siteprops.txt</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>/WEB-INF/meshcms/users/admin.txt</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusions</title>

    <para>I think that if the user does not need to customize stuff like
    sitemesh.xml or to upgrade a library, it is quite easy to upgrade MeshCMS.
    Advanced users should have the option to "lock" some components so they
    won't be upgraded. In this case, he should find somewhere an advice of
    what changes are required to that component.</para>
  </section>
</article>